Our mission is to build
مهمتنا تتركز في بناء
a detailed, realistic
كمبيوتر مفصل وواقعي
computer model of the human brain.
لتمثيل العقل البشري.
And we've done, in the past four years,
وقد أنهينا في الأربع سنين الماضية
a proof of concept
برهان للمفهوم
on a small part of the rodent brain,
على جزء صغير من عقل القوارض
and with this proof of concept we are now scaling the project up
و بهذا البرهان نحن الآن نجري توسعة لنطاق المشروع
to reach the human brain.
لكي يصل إلى العقل البشري .
Why are we doing this?
لماذا نقوم بعمل هذا الشيء؟
There are three important reasons.
هنالك ثلاثة أسباب هامه .
The first is, it's essential for us to understand the human brain
الأول هو, أنه من الأساسي بالنسبة لنا فهم العقل البشري
if we do want to get along in society,
إذا أردنا حقا أن ننسجم في المجتمع
and I think that it is a key step in evolution.
وأنا أعتقد أن هذا هو خطوة رئيسية في التطور
The second reason is,
السبب الثاني هو,
we cannot keep doing animal experimentation forever,
لا يمكننا إجراء التجارب المخبرية على الحيوانات إلى الأبد،
and we have to embody all our data and all our knowledge
وعلينا القيام بتجسيد جميع بياناتنا ومعارفنا،
into a working model.
في نموذج عامل
It's like a Noah's Ark. It's like an archive.
إنه كسفينة نوح . إنه كالأرشيف .
And the third reason is that there are two billion people on the planet
والسبب الثالث هو أن هنالك مليارين من البشر على هذا الكوكب
that are affected by mental disorder,
متأثرين بإضطرابات عقلية ،
and the drugs that are used today
والأدوية التي تستخدم اليوم
are largely empirical.
هي إلى حد كبير في مرحلة التجربة .
I think that we can come up with very concrete solutions on
أعتقد أننا يمكن أن نحصل على حلول واقعية للغاية تدور حول
how to treat disorders.
كيفية معالجة الإضطرابات .
Now, even at this stage,
الآن ، وحتى في هذه المرحلة ،
we can use the brain model
نستطيع استخدام نظام العقل
to explore some fundamental questions
لإستكشاف تساؤلات أساسية
about how the brain works.
حول كيفية عمل العقل .
And here, at TED, for the first time,
وهنا في تيد ، ولأول مرة ،
I'd like to share with you how we're addressing
أود أن أطلعكم على كيفية معالجتنا
one theory -- there are many theories --
نظرياً -- هنالك العديد من النظريات --
one theory of how the brain works.
نظرية واحدة حول كيفية عمل العقل .
So, this theory is that the brain
إذن ، هذه النظرية تدور حول أن العقل
creates, builds, a version of the universe,
ينشئ ، يبني ، نسخة من العالم .
and projects this version of the universe,
وتبرز هذه النسخة من الكون
like a bubble, all around us.
كفقاعة منتشرة حولنا في كل مكان .
Now, this is of course a topic of philosophical debate for centuries.
الآن ، أن هذا الموضوع بالتأكيد هو موضوع فلسفي جدلي استمر لقرون عدة .
But, for the first time, we can actually address this,
لكن ، وللمرة الأولى ، بإمكاننا فعليا أن نعالج هذه النظرية ،
with brain simulation,
بواسطة محاكاة العقل ،
and ask very systematic and rigorous questions,
ونطرح أسئلة دقيقة ومنهجية جدا ،
whether this theory could possibly be true.
ما إذا كانت هذه النظرية بإمكانها أن تكون صحيحة .
The reason why the moon is huge on the horizon
السبب وراء أن القمر يبدو كبيرا في الأفق
is simply because our perceptual bubble
هو ببساطة يعود لتخيل إدراكنا الحسي
does not stretch out 380,000 kilometers.
حيث لا يستطيع أن يمتد إلى 380 ألف كيلومترا .
It runs out of space.
لأن مساحتها تنفذ
And so what we do is we compare the buildings
وكذالك ما نقوم به حينما نقارن المباني
within our perceptual bubble,
داخل إدراكنا لفترة مؤقتة ,
and we make a decision.
و نقوم باتخاذ قرار .
We make a decision it's that big,
نحن نتخذ قرارا بأن هذه المباني كبيرة،
even though it's not that big.
على الرغم من أنها ليست كبيرة،
And what that illustrates
والذي يوضح ذلك هو
is that decisions are the key things
أن القرارات هي الأشياء الأساسية
that support our perceptual bubble. It keeps it alive.
التي تساند تخيل إدراكنا الحسي . إنها تبقيها حية .
Without decisions you cannot see, you cannot think,
من دون قرارات لا تستطيع أن ترى ،لا تستطيع أن تفكر،
you cannot feel.
لا تستطيع أن تشعر
And you may think that anesthetics work
وربما تعتقد أن التخدير يعمل
by sending you into some deep sleep,
على إرسالك إلى نوم عميق ،
or by blocking your receptors so that you don't feel pain,
أو يعمل على غلق أحاسيسك لكي لا تشعر بالألم ،
but in fact most anesthetics don't work that way.
لكن في الحقيقة أغلب أنواع التخدير لا تعمل بهذه الطريقة .
What they do is they introduce a noise
إنما الذى تفعله هو تسريب تشويش
into the brain so that the neurons cannot understand each other.
إلى العقل لكي لا تتمكن الخلايا العصبية من التعرف على بعضها البعض .
They are confused,
فتصبح مختلطة ومتخبطة ،
and you cannot make a decision.
ولن تستطيع بذلك إتخاذ أي قرار .
So, while you're trying to make up your mind
إذن، وبينما أنت تحاول أن تستعيد وعيك ،
what the doctor, the surgeon, is doing
مايفعله الدكتور , الجراح
while he's hacking away at your body, he's long gone.
بينما يقوم باختراق جسدك , قد ذهب بعيدً
He's at home having tea.
يكون في منزله يتناول قدحا من الشاي .
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So, when you walk up to a door and you open it,
إذن، عندما تسير نحو الباب لتقوم بفتحه ،
what you compulsively have to do to perceive
هو أنك وبشكل إلزامي تدرك أن عليك
is to make decisions,
القيام باتخاذ قرارات
thousands of decisions about the size of the room,
الآف القرارات حول حجم الغرفة ،
the walls, the height, the objects in this room.
الجدار، الإرتفاع ، الأثاث في هذه الغرفة .
99 percent of what you see
%99 مما تراه
is not what comes in through the eyes.
لا يأتي إلينا عبر العيون
It is what you infer about that room.
بل هو مانستنتجه حول تلك الغرفة .
So I can say, with some certainty,
لذلك أستطيع القول وبشيء من اليقين ،
"I think, therefore I am."
" أنا أفكر إذن أنا موجود. "
But I cannot say, "You think, therefore you are,"
لكنني لا أستطيع القول ، "أنت تفكر، إذن أنت موجود"
because "you" are within my perceptual bubble.
لأنك تقع داخل فقاعتي الإدراكية .
Now, we can speculate and philosophize this,
الآن، نستطيع أن نتوقع ونفلسف هذا الأمر،
but we don't actually have to for the next hundred years.
لكن في الواقع ليس من الضروري أن نبقى هكذا لمئات السنين القادمة
We can ask a very concrete question.
بإمكاننا طرح سؤال محدد جداً
"Can the brain build such a perception?"
" هل يستطيع العقل بناء مثل هذا الإدراك ؟"
Is it capable of doing it?
هل لديه الإمكانية لفعل ذلك ؟
Does it have the substance to do it?
هل لديه الجوهر والأساس للقيام بذلك ؟
And that's what I'm going to describe to you today.
وهذا ما سأقوم بشرحه لكم اليوم.
So, it took the universe 11 billion years to build the brain.
إذن ، إستغرق الكون 11 مليار سنة لبناء العقل .
It had to improve it a little bit.
كان هنالك حاجة لأن يحسنه قليلا
It had to add to the frontal part, so that you would have instincts,
كان لابد من أن يضيف الجزء الأمامي ، لكي يكون لديك الغرائز ,
because they had to cope on land.
لانهم اضطروا للحياه على الأرض .
But the real big step was the neocortex.
لكن الخطوة الحقيقية كانت القشرة المخية " النيوكورتكس ".
It's a new brain. You needed it.
إنه عقل جديد . كنت بحاجة له
The mammals needed it
الثدييات تحتاجها
because they had to cope with parenthood,
لأنها إضطرت للتأقلم مع الأبوة
social interactions,
التفاعلات الإجتماعية
complex cognitive functions.
الوظائف الإدراكية المعقدة .
So, you can think of the neocortex
إذن، تستطيع أن تعتبر القشرة المخية "نيوكورتيكس"
actually as the ultimate solution today,
اليوم تمثل الحل النهائي
of the universe as we know it.
للكون كما نعرفه.
It's the pinnacle, it's the final product
انها السقف الأعلى , انها المنتج النهائي
that the universe has produced.
الذي قام الكون بانتاجه
It was so successful in evolution
لقد كانت نجاحا هائلاً في التطور
that from mouse to man it expanded
التي توسعت من الفأر إلى الإنسان
about a thousandfold in terms of the numbers of neurons,
بحوالي ألف مرة من حيث عدد الخلايا العصبية
to produce this almost frightening
لإنتاج هذا الجزء الجسدى
organ, structure.
المخيف , تقريبا .
And it has not stopped its evolutionary path.
وهو لم يوقف مسار تطوره إلى الآن .
In fact, the neocortex in the human brain
في الحقيقة القشرة المخية "النيوكورتيكس" في العقل البشري
is evolving at an enormous speed.
تتطور بسرعة هائلة.
If you zoom into the surface of the neocortex,
إذا قمت بالتكبير داخل سطح القشرة المخية "النيوكورتيكس"،
you discover that it's made up of little modules,
ستكتشف أنها تتكون من وحدات صغيرة،
G5 processors, like in a computer.
معالجات الجيل الخامس كما نعرفها في الكمبيوتر.
But there are about a million of them.
ولكن هنالك الملايين منها.
They were so successful in evolution
لقد كانت ناجحة للغاية في التطور
that what we did was to duplicate them
مافعلناه كان القيام بمضاعفتها
over and over and add more and more of them to the brain
مرارا وتكرارا وإضافة المزيد منها إلى الدماغ
until we ran out of space in the skull.
حتى استهلكنا المساحة في الجمجمة.
And the brain started to fold in on itself,
وبدأ الدماغ الإضعاف على نفسه.
and that's why the neocortex is so highly convoluted.
وهذا مايفسر سبب أن القشرة المخية "النيوكورتيكس" معقدة للغاية.
We're just packing in columns,
قمنا بتجميعها في أعمدة
so that we'd have more neocortical columns
بحيث أصبح لدينا المزيد من أعمدة النيوكورتيكال
to perform more complex functions.
لأداء المزيد من الوظائف المعقدة.
So you can think of the neocortex actually as
إذن تستطيع تصور القشرة المخية "النيوكورتيكس" واقعيا على أنها
a massive grand piano,
أرضية بيانو ضخمة ،
a million-key grand piano.
ملايين مفاتيح بيانو .
Each of these neocortical columns
كل واحد من أعمدة النيوكورتيكال هذه
would produce a note.
تقوم بإنتاج نوتة.
You stimulate it; it produces a symphony.
إذا قمت بتنشيطها تنتج سيمفونية.
But it's not just a symphony of perception.
لكنها ليست مجرد سيمفونية للإدراك .
It's a symphony of your universe, your reality.
إنها سيمفونية الكون الخاص بك , إنها واقعك .
Now, of course it takes years to learn how
الآن , تتطلب عدة سنين لتتعلم كيف
to master a grand piano with a million keys.
تتقن البيانو الكبير الذي يتكون من مليون مفتاح .
That's why you have to send your kids to good schools,
لذلك السبب يجب أن ترسل أبنائك إلى مدارس جيدة ,
hopefully eventually to Oxford.
ربما إلى أكسفورد في نهاية المطاف .
But it's not only education.
لكنه لا يقتصر على التعليم
It's also genetics.
بل أيضا على الجينات .
You may be born lucky,
ربما تولد محظوظاً ,
where you know how to master your neocortical column,
أو كيف تتحكم فى محور الجزء الخارجى للمخ ,
and you can play a fantastic symphony.
ويمكنك أن تعزف سيمفونية رائعة .
In fact, there is a new theory of autism
فى الحقيقة , هناك نظرية جديدة للأوتسم ( عدم النمو الطبيعى للعقل )
called the "intense world" theory,
تسمى نظرية " العالم الكثيف " ,
which suggests that the neocortical columns are super-columns.
التى تقترح أن تكون محاور الجزء الخارجى للمخ على درجة عالية من القدرة .
They are highly reactive, and they are super-plastic,
إنهم على درجة عالية من رد الفعل , وعلى درجة جيدة من البلاستيك ,
and so the autists are probably capable of
ومرضى الأوتزم من المحتمل أن يكونوا قادرين على
building and learning a symphony
بناء و تعْلم سيمفونية
which is unthinkable for us.
الأمر الذى لم نفكر به على الإطلاق .
But you can also understand
لكنكم أيضاً تستطيعون أن تفهموا
that if you have a disease
أنكم فى حاله مرضكم بمرض
within one of these columns,
من هذه المحاور ,
the note is going to be off.
الملاحظة ستكون سلبية .
The perception, the symphony that you create
الإدراك , السيمفونية التى ألفتمونها
is going to be corrupted,
ستكون فى طريقها للفساد ,
and you will have symptoms of disease.
وستظهر عليك أعراض المرض .
So, the Holy Grail for neuroscience
لذا , فالكأس المقدسة للعلوم العصبية
is really to understand the design of the neocoritical column --
هو بالحقيقة لفهم التصميم الخاص بالمحور العصبى --
and it's not just for neuroscience;
وهو ليس فقط لعلم الأعصاب :
it's perhaps to understand perception, to understand reality,
من المحتمل لفهم قدرة الشخص , لفهم الحقيقة ,
and perhaps to even also understand physical reality.
ومن المحتمل أيضاً أن تكون لفهم الحقيقة الفيزيائية .
So, what we did was, for the past 15 years,
لذا , ما فعلناه هو , فى الخمسة عشر عاماً الماضية ,
was to dissect out the neocortex, systematically.
كان تشريح القشرة العقلية , بإنتظام .
It's a bit like going and cataloging a piece of the rainforest.
إنه قليل الشبه بأخذ قطعة من كل أجزاء الغابة
How many trees does it have?
كم شجرة تحتوي هذه الغابة ؟
What shapes are the trees?
ما هو شكل هذه الأشجار ؟
How many of each type of tree do you have? Where are they positioned?
كم شجرة من كل نوع من تلك الأشجار لديك؟ ما هو موقعهم بالتحديد ؟
But it's a bit more than cataloging because you actually have to
لكنه أكثر من تشبيهه بالتجميع لأنك فى الحقيقة لابد من أن
describe and discover all the rules of communication,
تصف وتكتشف كل قواعد الإتصالات ,
the rules of connectivity,
قواعد التواصل بينهم ,
because the neurons don't just like to connect with any neuron.
لأن الخلايا العصبية لا تتواصل مع أية خلية عصبية .
They choose very carefully who they connect with.
إنهم يختارون بعناية فائقة منْ مِن الخلايا سيتصلون .
It's also more than cataloging
إنه أكثر من تشبيهه بالتجميع
because you actually have to build three-dimensional
لأنه فى الحقيقة لابد أن تبنى نماذج ثلاثية الأبعاد
digital models of them.
رقمية لهم .
And we did that for tens of thousands of neurons,
ونحن فعلنا ذلك لعشرات الآلاف من العصبونات,
built digital models of all the different types
التى بُنيت من نماذج رقمية لكل الأنواع المختلفة
of neurons we came across.
للعصبونات التى تعرضنا لها .
And once you have that, you can actually
وبمجرد أن تحصلوا على ذلك , بالفعل تستطيعون
begin to build the neocortical column.
أن تبدأوا فى بناء عمود النيوكورتيكال .
And here we're coiling them up.
ونحن هنا نصطفهم بشكل دائرى .
But as you do this, what you see
لكن بفعلكم ذلك , ما ترونه
is that the branches intersect
هو تلك التقاطعات بينهم
actually in millions of locations,
فى ملايين من الأماكن الفعلية .
and at each of these intersections
وفى كل واحد من هذه التقاطعات
they can form a synapse.
يكونون سينبس ( مكان تقابل الخلايا العصبية )
And a synapse is a chemical location
و السينبس هو مكان كيميائى
where they communicate with each other.
حيث أنهم يستطيعون التواصل مع بعضهم البعض .
And these synapses together
وهذه السينابسس معاً
form the network
يشكلون شبكة
or the circuit of the brain.
أو دائرة تدفق المعلومات فى المخ .
Now, the circuit, you could also think of as
الآن , الدائرة , يمكن أن تفكروا بها ك
the fabric of the brain.
نظام عمل علاقات المخ .
And when you think of the fabric of the brain,
وعندما تفكرون بهذا النظام ,
the structure, how is it built? What is the pattern of the carpet?
التنظيم , كيفية بنائه ؟ ما هى منظومة عمل السجاد ؟
You realize that this poses
تدركون أن هذه المواضع
a fundamental challenge to any theory of the brain,
هى تحدى أساسى لأى نظرية لعمل العقل ,
and especially to a theory that says
وبالأخص لنظرية تقول
that there is some reality that emerges
أن هناك بعض الحقيقة تبدو
out of this carpet, out of this particular carpet
لنا من هذا السجاد , من هذا الرسم بالأخص
with a particular pattern.
بنموذج محدد .
The reason is because the most important design secret of the brain
السبب هو أن أهم تصميم سرى للعقل
is diversity.
هو الإختلاف .
Every neuron is different.
كل خلية عصبية تختلف عن غيرها .
It's the same in the forest. Every pine tree is different.
نفس الشيئ فى الغابة . كل شجيرة تختلف عن غيرها .
You may have many different types of trees,
من الممكن أن يكون هناك أنواع مختلفة من الأشجار ,
but every pine tree is different. And in the brain it's the same.
لكن كل شجيرة تختلف عن غيرها . وفى المخ نفس الشيئ .
So there is no neuron in my brain that is the same as another,
حسناً لا توجد خلية عصبية فى عقلى تطابق خلية أخرى ,
and there is no neuron in my brain that is the same as in yours.
وليس هناك خلية عصبية فى مخى تطابق خلية فى عقلكم .
And your neurons are not going to be oriented and positioned
وخلاياكم العصبية لن تكون لها نفس الخصائص أو الأماكن
in exactly the same way.
بنفس الطريقة بالضبط .
And you may have more or less neurons.
ومن الممكن أن تكونوا عندكم من الخلايا العصبية أكثر أو أقل .
So it's very unlikely
لذا فمن المستبعد جداً
that you got the same fabric, the same circuitry.
أن يكون لديكم نفس المكونات , نفس الدوائر الكهربية .
So, how could we possibly create a reality
لذا , كيف لنا أن نكوْن حقيقة
that we can even understand each other?
أننا نستطيع أن نفهم كل واحد منها ؟
Well, we don't have to speculate.
حسناً , لن نضطر أن نخمن .
We can look at all 10 million synapses now.
نستطيع أن ننظر الآن إلى عشرة ملايين من السينابسس .
We can look at the fabric. And we can change neurons.
نستطيع أن ننظر إلى التركيبة .ونستطيع أن نغير الخلايا العصبية .
We can use different neurons with different variations.
نستطيع أن نستخدم خلايا عصبية مختلفة إختلافات بسيطة .
We can position them in different places,
نستطيع أن نضعهم فى أماكن مختلفة ,
orient them in different places.
وتوجيههم إلى أماكن مختلفة .
We can use less or more of them.
نستطيع أن نستخدم أعداد أكثر أو أقل منهم .
And when we do that
وعندما نفعل ذلك
what we discovered is that the circuitry does change.
إكتشفنا أن دائرة الخلايا العصبية تتغير بالفعل .
But the pattern of how the circuitry is designed does not.
لكن كيفية عمل تصميم هذه الدائرة لا يتغير .
So, the fabric of the brain,
لذا , تركيبة المخ ,
even though your brain may be smaller, bigger,
حتى لو أن المخ أصغر أو أكبر ,
it may have different types of neurons,
يمكن أن يكون به أنواع مختلفة من الخلايا العصبية ,
different morphologies of neurons,
أشكال مختلفة من الخلايا العصبية ,
we actually do share
نحن بالفعل نتشارك
the same fabric.
نفس التركيبة .
And we think this is species-specific,
ونعتقد أن هذا هو التصنيف المحدد ,
which means that that could explain
الذى يعنى بدوره ويمكن تفسير
why we can't communicate across species.
لماذا لا نستطيع أن نتواصل خلال التصنيف .
So, let's switch it on. But to do it, what you have to do
لذا , دعونا نشغلها . لكن لكى نفعل ذلك , الذى لابد من عمله
is you have to make this come alive.
هو أنه لابد من أن تدعوها للحياه .
We make it come alive
نحن نبث بها الحياه
with equations, a lot of mathematics.
بمعادلات رياضية , كثير من الرياضيات .
And, in fact, the equations that make neurons into electrical generators
وفى الحقيقة ,هذه المعادلات هى التى تحول الخلايا العصبية إلى محولات كهربية
were discovered by two Cambridge Nobel Laureates.
كانت قد إكتُشفت بواسطة إثنين من العلماء الحائزين على جائزة نوبل .
So, we have the mathematics to make neurons come alive.
لذا , نحن نملك الرياضيات اللازمة لجعل هذه الخلايا تعمل كما هى الحال داخل العقل .
We also have the mathematics to describe
أيضاً نملك من الرياضيات لوصف
how neurons collect information,
كيف تجمع هذه الخلايا معلومات ,
and how they create a little lightning bolt
وكيف تخلق ضوء بسيط أو شعاع
to communicate with each other.
فيما بينها للتواصل مع بعضها البعض .
And when they get to the synapse,
وعندما تصل إلى السنيبس ,
what they do is they effectively,
الذى تفعله بدقه تامه ,
literally, shock the synapse.
أن تصدم السنيبس بحرفيه شديدة ,
It's like electrical shock
مثل الصدمه الكهربية
that releases the chemicals from these synapses.
التى بدورها تحرر المواد الكيميائية من هذه السنيبسس ( مشابك الخلايا ) .
And we've got the mathematics to describe this process.
ونحن نملك الرياضيات لوصف هذا السيناريو .
So we can describe the communication between the neurons.
نستطيع أن نصف الإتصالات بين الخلايا العصبية .
There literally are only a handful
بالحقيقة هناك ما يوازى ملء كف اليد
of equations that you need to simulate
من المعادلات التى تحتاجها لتحفيز
the activity of the neocortex.
نشاط القشرة الخارجية للمخ .
But what you do need is a very big computer.
لكن ما تحتاجه هو سوبر كمبيوتر .
And in fact you need one laptop
وأيضاً نحتاج لابتوب (كمبيوتر صغير )
to do all the calculations just for one neuron.
لعمل كل التكاملات اللازمة لخلية عصبية واحدة فقط .
So you need 10,000 laptops.
لذا نحتاج 10,000 لابتوب .
So where do you go? You go to IBM,
حسناً إلى أين نذهب ؟ تذهبون إلى IBM ,
and you get a supercomputer, because they know how to take
وتحصلوا على سوبر كمبيوتر ,لأنهم يعرفون كيف يأخذون
10,000 laptops and put it into the size of a refrigerator.
10,000 لابتوب ويضعونها فى شيئ حجمه مثل حجم الثلاجة .
So now we have this Blue Gene supercomputer.
لذا الآن عندنا هذا السوبر كمبيوتر الأزرق ,المعروف ب ( نيويورك الأزرق ) .
We can load up all the neurons,
نستطيع أن نحمل عليه كل الخلايا العصبية ,
each one on to its processor,
على كل معالج خاص بالابتوب ,
and fire it up, and see what happens.
ونبدأ العمل , ونرى ما يحدث .
Take the magic carpet for a ride.
نأخذ جولة طيران بداخله لنرى .
Here we activate it. And this gives the first glimpse
هنا نحن أدرناه . وهذا يعطينا أول إضاءة
of what is happening in your brain
لما يحدث فى عقلك
when there is a stimulation.
عندما يكون هناك حافز ما .
It's the first view.
إنها أول رؤية .
Now, when you look at that the first time, you think,
الآن , عندما تنظرون إليها لأول وهلة , تعتقدون ,
"My god. How is reality coming out of that?"
" يا إلهى . كيف تخرج الحقيقة من ذلك الشيئ ؟ "
But, in fact, you can start,
لكن , فى الحقيقة , تستطيعون أن تبدأوا ,
even though we haven't trained this neocortical column
حتى بالرغم عدم تدريب تلك محاور القشرة الخارجية
to create a specific reality.
لتخليق حقيقة محددة .
But we can ask, "Where is the rose?"
لكننا نستطيع أن نسأل , " أين الوردة ؟ "
We can ask, "Where is it inside,
نسأل , " أين هى بالداخل ,
if we stimulate it with a picture?"
لو أننا حفزناها مع صورة ؟ "
Where is it inside the neocortex?
أين هى داخل القشرة الداخلية ؟
Ultimately it's got to be there if we stimulated it with it.
فى النهاية لابد أن تكون هناك لو أننا حفزناها بالصورة .
So, the way that we can look at that
لذا , الطريق الذى نستطيع أن ننظر إليه
is to ignore the neurons, ignore the synapses,
هو أن نتجاهل الخلايا العصبية , أن نتجاهل السنيبسس ,
and look just at the raw electrical activity.
وننظر فقط إلى خط نشاط الكهرباء .
Because that is what it's creating.
لأن ذلك هو ما يكونها أو يخلقها .
It's creating electrical patterns.
إنها تخلق نماذج كهربية .
So when we did this,
عندما فعلنا هذا ,
we indeed, for the first time,
فى الحقيقة , إنها المرة الأولى ,
saw these ghost-like structures:
التى نرى هذه الأرواح تبدو كبناء متكامل :
electrical objects appearing
مظهر العناصر الكهربية
within the neocortical column.
خلال أعمدة الأعصاب .
And it's these electrical objects
وهذه العناصر الكهربية
that are holding all the information about
هى التى تحتوى كل المعلومات عن
whatever stimulated it.
أى شيئ يحفزها .
And then when we zoomed into this,
وعند ذلك عندما كبرناها إلى هذا الحجم ,
it's like a veritable universe.
إنها مثل عالمك المحبوب .
So the next step
فالخطوة التالية
is just to take these brain coordinates
هى أن تأخذ هذه التجميعة المخية
and to project them into perceptual space.
وتصنع منها أو تحولها إلى مجال إدراك حسى .
And if you do that,
وإذا فعلت ذلك ,
you will be able to step inside
تستطيع أن تكون لك القدرة للدخول إلى داخل
the reality that is created
الحقيقة التى خُلقت أو تكونت
by this machine,
بهذه الماكينة ,
by this piece of the brain.
لهذا الجزء من العقل .
So, in summary,
لذا , فى إيجاز ,
I think that the universe may have --
أعتقد أن العالم المفضل من الممكن أن --
it's possible --
من المحتمل --
evolved a brain to see itself,
تطورت العقل ليرى نفسة,
which may be a first step in becoming aware of itself.
الشيء الذى يعتبر خطوة أولى فى طريق إدراك ذاتة .
There is a lot more to do to test these theories,
هناك الكثير الذي ينبغي عمله لاختبار هذه النظريات ،
and to test any other theories.
ولإختبار أي نظريات أخرى.
But I hope that you are at least partly convinced
ولكن أرجو أن تكونو على الأقل مقتنعين إلى حد ما
that it is not impossible to build a brain.
أنه ليس من المستحيل بناء عقل .
We can do it within 10 years,
ويمكننا القيام بذلك في غضون 10 سنوات
and if we do succeed,
و إذا نجحنا
we will send to TED, in 10 years,
سوف نرسل إلى تد ، في 10 سنين
a hologram to talk to you. Thank you.
صورة ثلاثية الأبعاد لأتحدث إليكم . شكرا لكم .
(Applause)
(تصفيق)